[Music]
thank you
all right
welcome it is active live stream number
51.0
this is the background in context first
discussion for canonical neural networks
perform active inference by isomera at
all it's October 26 2022.
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at some of the links on
the page this is a recorded in an
archived live stream so please provide
us with feedback so we can improve our
work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will be following video
etiquette for solo live streams
head to activeinference.org to learn how
to get involved with active inference
Institute projects
today it's the first of several
discussions that we'll have on the paper
canonical neural networks perform active
inference 2022 by takuya isamura
hideyaki shimazaki and Carl friston the
video is just an introduction to some of
the ideas it's not a review or final
word
there will be an overview of the
structure of the paper and then we'll go
through many of the key points also just
to disclaim there's many many
other and better resources to learn
about neural networks so I would very
much welcome those with a technical
understanding of neural networks and or
some of the more applied
computational or uh
otherwise aspects of neural networks it
would be awesome to have them on for the
dot one and the dot two because it was
not an area I was familiar with and so
hope that I can
hear more from the authors in our coming
weeks and others
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and this will just be a
solo.0 which I guess hasn't happened in
a while
in the making of this here are some of
the generated art prompts Area 51 active
inference
Area 51 neural network Area 51 active
inference ants Area 51 active inference
neural network
just some interesting images coming out
of stable diffusion
so as to some big questions that the
paper is addressing and that one might
be interested in to come to the paper
how can artificial neural networks be
understood as generic optimization
processes and what is the correspondence
between neurodynamics and modern
statistical inference methods
other big questions are uh about the
history and next steps of the enmeshment
of natural intelligence EG neuroscience
and artificial intelligence as well as
of course whether to even play into this
kind of Distinction at all and have
different integrated intelligence
Frameworks
and one paper where any of the authors
or anyone who has uh kind of resonated
with this work is recent buys a door at
all 2022 towards the Next Generation
artificial intelligence catalyzing the
neuro AI Revolution and so this is a
bunch of authors and so it's interesting
just to quote in terms of what some
areas of discourse are saying right now
which is neuroscience has long been an
important driver of progress in
artificial intelligence AI we propose
that to accelerate progress in AI we
must invest in fundamental research in
neuro AI so that's one way to bead some
of the developments that are happening
in the paper we'll discuss
uh what does it mean to be particular
but generic that's a phrase used in the
paper so maybe that's kind of a jumping
off point and then how can active
inference help us understand the past
present and future
here of the interface with neural
network statistics and neural AI
here's the abstract
this work considers a class of canonical
neural networks comprising rate coding
models where a neural activity in
plasticity minimize a common cost
function and plasticity is modulated
with a certain delay
we show that such neural networks
implicitly perform active inference in
learning to minimize the risk associated
with future outcomes mathematical
analyzes demonstrate that this
biological optimization can be cast as
maximization of model evidence
or equivalently minimization of
variational free energy
under the well-known form of a partially
observed Markov decision process model
this equivalence indicates that the
delayed modulation of habian plasticity
accompanied with adaptation of firing
thresholds is the sufficient neuronal
substrate to attain Bayes optimal
inference and control we corroborated
this proposition using numerical
analyzes of maze tasks
this Theory offers a universal
characterization of canonical neural
networks in terms of Bayesian belief
updating and provides insight into the
neuronal mechanism's underlying planning
and adaptive behavioral control
here is the roadmap
I'll be driving on the right side of the
road
there's an introduction and a table with
glossary of different Expressions used
then there's the results sections which
has a first an overview of equivalence
between neural networks and variational
Bays
active inference formulated using a
postdiction of past decisions canonical
neural networks perform active inference
and numerical simulations so they work
on the interface between neural networks
and variational Bayesian methods
and start with a more theoretical
and mathematical backgrounds and then
eventually present some maze simulations
that are in Matlab then there's a
discussion and then the methods section
is following the discussion
and it has the subsections generative
model variational free energy inference
in learning neural networks simulations
and data analysis and
I think that I have kept to the right
color codes consistently from here on
forward the block quotes are the direct
quotes from the paper blue codes quotes
are related to perception
uh orange for Action complete class
theorems and neural networks together in
purple and then red is commentary and
then the highlighting for red is related
to um
the variational methods but it's kind of
red ish
okay the papers canonical neural
networks perform active inference by the
authors uh listed previously it's in
Communications biology
from 2022.
and the key aims of the paper are laid
out well in the first paragraph so
that's in black and other colors and uh
here the red is just kind of
getting into initial conversation with
the paper and connecting a little bit
more to some previous streams before we
go more into the specifics of the paper
the sentient behavior of biological
organisms is characterized by
optimization
biological organisms recognize the state
of their environment by optimizing
internal representations of the external
environmental Dynamics generating
sensory inputs so that's the sensory
recognition model
in addition they optimize their behavior
for adaptation to the environment
thereby increasing their probability of
survival and reproduction
so that is bringing the entire active
and inactive
control theory formal theories of action
action selections planning and planning
as inference all of these
action-oriented pragmatic turn type
ideas come into play when this action
orange aspect is brought in and
it is slash must be slash should be
Etc oriented towards survival and
persistence
otherwise we don't see that kind of
thing for long over appropriate
definitions for thing and log Etc
and uh this few sentences that the paper
begins with summarizes
a common theme in active which is that
there's basically two Pathways towards
Proficiency in the niche there's
changing the mind which is the
perceptual and learning and then there's
changing the world through action and
that kind of integration of inference
cognitive inference whether it's
perceptual or learning or other and
action as enacted is part of the active
formulism and shared with other areas
this biological self-organization is
typically formulated as the minimization
of cost functions where in a gradient
descent on a cost function furnishes
neurodynamics and synaptic plasticity
so they are working with a framework
where the way that this perception
action flow
is tractable computationally either just
for our current computers so that we can
Implement simulations and data fitting
or whether more fundamentally like this
is the computational context of action
they're suggesting there's a way to
think of it in terms of a cost function
minimization
and also note like minimization
maximization in a way they're
interchangeable because there's just
sometimes negative signs that can flip
them so it's the same energy and fitness
landscape
that is being navigated whether you're
minimizing to the bottom of the bowl and
thinking of action selection that way
and inference or whether you're climbing
to the top of the hill gradient descent
gradient Ascent they're both kind of two
sides the same coin
um
two fundamental issues remain to be
established namely
so what this is what the paper is saying
they're filling the Gap in literature
the characterization of the Dynamics of
an arbitrary neural network as a generic
optimization process
and the correspondence between such
neurodynamics and statistical inference
found in Applied Mathematics machine
learning the present work addresses
these issues by demonstrating that a
class of canonical neural networks of
rape coding models is functioning as and
thus universally characterized in terms
of variational Bayesian inference under
a particular but generic form of the
generative model
this is maybe the only slide that has
resources from
too far afield from the paper well
almost a few more
it's just on neural networks
the search on a very common Search tool
resulted in five plus Million results
for what are neural networks and the
first one was three blue one Brown from
2017 which is just a nice YouTube video
as they very often make with these
beautiful Renditions
and it's a very great video and there's
many many others a neural network is a
network or Circuit of biological neurons
and that is variously purely
computational and or biological
map territory stuff
and they can be thought of as nodes and
edges which are
um the firing rates and the connections
between the biological neurons being
modeled as weights between nodes
a positive weight reflects an excitatory
connection while negative values mean
inhibitory connections and here is data
coming in and ending up activating
different neurons in this final layer so
this is kind of doing inference in a
neural net work and then there's an
action part okay
the paper says variational Bayesian
inference offers a unified explanation
for inference learning prediction
decision making and the evolution of
biological form which can be considered
over multiple time scales so this
returns to the earlier theme of like
perception action
and
persistence within and among generations
and the citations that are provided here
for this are friston Kilner Harrison
2006 and friston 2010 both very classic
active slash
fepers just to show one figure from each
here's from
the first citation with the winged
snowflake where if the snowflake ends up
being somewhere that's too warm
that's not able for it to maintain the
structure then it melts
melts into a dew Etc and
it must be acting as if in one way or
another it's staying above that phase
boundary that's how it's statistically
identified it's how it's
autogenetically identified functionally
identified
and then here is one of the
um
kind of path setting
figures in the first in 2010 paper with
a tree
of many different
areas to connect to and formalisms to
represent as including probabilistic
neural coding
Bayesian brain
optimal control and value learning
these three and others
can be really seen at play in this 2022
paper
uh the kind of inference variational
Bayesian methods use rest upon a
generative model that expresses a
hypothesis about the generation of
sensory input
perception and behavior can then be read
as optimizing the evidence for a
generative model inherent and sensory
exchanges for the environment
and that's the integration of perception
and action within a single imperative
in terms of if only computation
and that is described more on this slide
which one can pause and read but the
rest of the quotes are from
the paper
uh one
e formalism
that I had no familiarity with before
this
paper and Associated readings and
conversations with Ali
was the complete class theorem so it
would be
um great for anyone who's familiar with
complete class theorem to
help a little bit here but here's some
interesting things that I came across
crucially from the paper as a corollary
of the complete class theorem citations
19-21 any neural network minimizing a
cost function can be viewed as
performing variational Bayesian
inference under some prior beliefs
here are the citations 19 through 21
from 1947 1981 2013.
and uh also found some
interesting resources so quoting from
this less wrong post linked here
Dutch book defines belief as willingness
to bet and money pump defines preference
as willingness to pay
this is in terms of the foundational
Arguments for a Bayesian epistemological
worldview
hope that's correct again it'd be good
to
hear from anyone who knows more here but
in terms of different ways that one can
consider the Bayesian
proposition
which perhaps these are even better to
use than referencing any person's last
name because the interesting thing will
be the different
uh lenses that these different framings
on Bayesian
probabilities
are interpreted as just like what a
p-value is interpreted as in the
frequentist world common obviously like
a base Factor interpretation
so Dutch book defines belief as
willingness to bet and money pump
defines preferences willingness to pay
in doing so both arguments put the
justification of decision Theory into
hypothetical exploitation scenarios
which are not quite the same as the
actual decisions we face
if these were the best justifications
for consequentialism we could muster I
would be somewhat dissatisfied but would
likely leave it alone
fortunately a better alternative exists
the complete class theorem
so here's an image from
that post
able World States observation likelihood
maps to the possible observations
hashtag a matrix then decision making
rule may be probabilistic
action selection as inference a possible
actions
affordances
and here we commonly see the loop being
closed from actions to World States like
through the B Matrix changing how the
world changes through time and here
these are both going to be mapped to a
loss function l
a real valued score from taking an
action a when the world turned out to be
Theta realized Theta
so that's quite an interesting framing
and there were some other useful posts
online and from this uh zhat blog
the argument boils down to if you agree
with expected utility as your objective
then you have to be Bayesian
in a nutshell a strategy is inadmissible
if there exists another strategy that is
as good in all situations and strictly
better in at least one
if you want your strategy to be
admissible
it should be equivalent to a Bayes
estimator
complete complete class theorems
only base strategies are admissible and
admissible strategies are based
so
there's probably a lot of
interpretations of this but it seems
kind of related to Optimal control or
base optimal inference perhaps a little
bit more keenly
so these are some
next two slides were contributed by Ali
so if you or if anyone familiar in this
area wants to come on in the discussion
to be great
but uh Ali pointed me to this book
fundamentals of Bayesian epistemology by
title bomb 2022 the table of contents
shown here
and some challenges and objections to
Bayesian epistemology are listed which
can be read
and then also there's some quite
interesting logical structures which can
be read here in terms of their premise
theorem and conclusion
in the areas of arguments for
bayesianism being representation theorem
argument for probabilism
the Dutch book argument for probabilism
and the gradational accuracy argument
for probabilism
so pretty interesting
back to the paper
they wrote we have previously introduced
a reverse engineering approach that
identifies a class of biologically
plausible cost functions for neural
networks
citation 22.
previous paper of isomura and friston
the paper was reverse engineering neural
networks to characterize their cost
functions
the abstract shown here but this letter
considers a class of biologically
plausible cost functions for neural
networks
using generative models based on
partially observable Markov decision
processes pomdp
we show that neural activity and
plasticity perform Bayesian inference
and learning respectively by maximizing
model evidence so this is a precursor
paper from 2020 that is cited and
foundational for the 2022 paper
here's some figures from that paper
they have a comparisons among a Markov
decision process scheme and a neural
network
for example a Markov decision process
scheme expressed as a Forney Factor
graph
based on the formulation in friston
so here is the Markov decision process
as a 40 Factor graph and on the right
side is the neural network
with the hidden State sensory inputs and
neural activity and some
figures
and concordances
and they wrote in this context the
neural network can principle be used as
a dynamic causal model to estimate
threshold constants and implicit priors
this reverse engineering speaks to
estimating the priors used by real
neuronal systems under ideal Bayesian
assumptions sometimes referred to as
metabasian inference so they're
laying out their research agenda
and
much of the work is going to reference
this earlier paper and other work
and then there's also some new
Integrations and
especially the maze simulation in this
paper and probably more so let's find
out
referring to the earlier paper
this foundational work identified a
class of cost functions for single layer
field feed forward neural networks of
rate coding models with a sigmoid or
logistic activation function
we subsequently demonstrated that
mathematical equivalence between the
class of cost functions for such neural
networks and variational free energy
under a particular form of the
generative model which is similar
broadly to what the 22 paper does to
this equivalence licenses variational
Bayesian inference as a fundamental
optimization process that underlies both
the Dynamics and function of such neural
networks
however it remains to be established
whether the active inference
is an apt explanation for any given
neural network that actively exchanges
with its environment
in this paper we address this inactive
or control aspect to complete the formal
equivalence of neural network
optimization and the free energy
principle
so this
earlier work
was not including action
and so this paper's key
Edition
as I understand it hopefully
is that they
bring action
more formally into the model
and it'd be interesting to know like
what else is that change associated with
or what else
happens or doesn't
um here's some more
text about the approach that they're
going to take
and many of these details are going to
be addressed later on
here's table one
glossary of expressions
so these will also be broadly
addressed later on
maybe it's useful though just to read
the first one a canonical neural network
in this work the canonical neural
network is defined by differential
equations of neural activity derived as
a reduction of realistic neuron models
through some approximations
which give a network of rate coding
neurons with the sigmoid activation
function
in particular we consider networks
comprising a middle layer that involves
recurrent connections
and the output layer that provides
feedback responses to the environment
so some category of neural network
architectures
or anatomies physiologies whatever
with sensory cognitive and action like
features in an environment or a
generative process
so the results section
they write
an overview of equivalence between
neural networks and variational base
first we summarize the formal
correspondence between neural networks
and variational base a biological agent
is formulated here as an autonomous
system comprising a network of rate
coding neurons figure one a so here's a
small figure 1A we'll see it larger
based upon the assumptions which will be
brought up later on in a different
folder form
the update rule for the ith component of
Phi
which is the internal States so the
cognitive States and the output layer y
so middle layer X and output layer y
these can be seen as the cognitive and
the action selective aspects which are
the autonomous States
in contrast to the particular states of
the active inference entity which is the
whole blanket and the cognitive States
so including the sensory States but the
sensory States can't be directly
controlled however action can influence
them and so that's what closes the
causal Loop
and that particular that set of the
particular States comprising the
autonomous States
the update rule for the ith component of
Phi is derived as the gradient descent
on the cost function
so the change in that by sub I is
proportional to a derivative on the loss
function
this determines the Dynamics of neural
networks including their activity in
plasticity so L common loss function o
observations sensory States
by internal States comprised in the
middle and output layer neural activity
that's the rate coding part and synoptic
strengths W the parameterization
and other free parameters including that
they characterize l
then there's the output layer activity Y
is determining the Network's actions or
decisions
Delta
O X and Y why is the outputting action
environment generative process hidden
State passing observations to the
sensory cognitive octave layers the
neural network
and that is analogous
topologically to the variational
Bayesian formulation
in figure 1B
and so left side gradient descent on a
neural network cost function L
determines the Dynamics of neural
activity and plasticity thus L is
sufficient to characterize the neural
network
and then being
shown next to on the right side
variational free energy minimization
allows an agent to self-organize
to encode the hidden states of the
external milieu and to make decisions
minimizing future risk here variational
free energy f is sufficient to
characterize the inferences and
behaviors of the agent
so sentence structure parallelism and
these two
schemes or approaches being linked and
applied is
a focus of this area
so neural networks are minimizing the
cost function l in contrast variational
Bayesian inference depicts a process of
updating the prior distribution of
external States P of theta so the
corresponding posterior distribution Q
of theta based upon the sequence of
observations
and we see other familiar terms from
discussions on variational days like
minimization of surprise
and there's some more model details
shown here
a few points are about choosing the
family of distributions that one is
doing variational inference with
and that allows for the gradient update
rules in that family of distributions to
be made simpler
for example choosing a linear regression
with an L2 Norm at the very least you
can say that it has a simple decision
rule for Being Fit I'm sure there's like
also counter arguments and other
algorithms that are better and so on but
just to say that a simple decision rule
in a known family of distributions can
often be good enough as an approximation
if not more
crucially according to the complete
class theorem
from earlier
A dynamical system that minimizes its
cost function can be viewed as
performing Bayesian inference under some
generative model and prior beliefs the
complete class theorem goes on to
describe it
ensures the presence of a generative
model that formally corresponds to the
above defined neural network
characterized by L hence this speaks to
the equivalence between the class of
neural network cost functions and
variational free energy under such a
generative model equation one
loss function on the time series of
observations comma parameters
three lines is defined as F the free
energy function on the same o
Through Time
comma parameters
so there's a
parallel being
shown slash defined
wherein the internal states of a network
Phi encode or parameterize the posterior
expectation
Theta
this mathematical equivalence means that
an arbitrary neural network in the class
under consideration is implicitly
performing active inference through
variational free energy minimization
and more is written but this is one of
many statements that will be made
corresponding to
correspondences between
neural network loss function generative
model octave free energy minimization
and associated formalisms
note that being able to characterize the
neural network in terms of maximizing
model evidence lends it and
explainability
in the sense that internal neural
network States and parameters encode
Bayesian beliefs or expectations about
the causes of observations
in other words the generative model
explains how outcomes were generated
however the complete class theorem does
not specify the form of a generative
model for any given neural network
to address this issue in the remainder
of the paper we formulate active
inference using a particular form of
partially observable Markov decision
processes pomdp models whose States take
binary values so this is one of several
simplifications is one way to see it or
areas for later generalization
figure two in this section we Define a
generative model and ensuing variational
free energy that corresponds to a class
of canonical neural networks that will
be considered in the subsequent section
the external milieu is expressed as a
discrete State space in the form of a
pomdp figure two
so
to make figure two larger
there's a lot to probably say about this
bigger
I'll just
note that the caption is informative and
some of the highlighted lines
it'll be awesome to have the author and
other people who's familiar
with some of the differences and
symmetries between the for example
bottom and top
above and below the observations
and also about the role of time
and what these two risks are what is
fictive causality
here's more details on that pomdp
then equation two
this is in this section active inference
formulated using a postdiction of past
decisions so if it was a prediction of
future decisions it's this the opposite
a postdiction of past decisions
hence we Define the generative model as
follows
p o Delta s gamma data which is the
model of observations decisions
observations decisions hidden States
risk and data
uh
theta equals a b and c
constitutes the set of parameters
and more details are provided
this is the familiar notation
with some slight differences that'll be
described and equation two reflects the
factorizability
and the dimensions and the kind of
computational tractability
expression
so that would be interesting to also
learn about like under what conditions
can this joint distribution be
factorized
under what simplifications or
constructions
the agent is making decisions to
minimize a risk function Capital gamma
that's on the bottom of figure two
evictive causality leading to this gamma
coming from dot gamma
equation three is shown
and to characterize the optimal
decisions as minimizing expected risk in
our pomdp model we use a victim mapping
from the current risk gamma to past
decisions that's that retroductive
victim causality
although this is not the true causality
in the real generative process that
generates sensory data here we intend to
model the manner that an agent
subjectively evaluates its previous
decisions After experiencing their
consequences this fictive causality is
expressed in the form of a categorical
distribution
so it could be other families
hypothetically
but this equation 3 is describing
evictive causality and this interesting
sign
indicates the element-wise division
operator also note throughout the
manuscript the overline variable
indicates one minus that variable so
gamma bar equals one minus Gamma or it
can be understood as the complement of a
statistical probability
probability of a happening and the
probability of not a happening in that
one way
importantly the agent needs to keep
selecting good decisions while avoiding
bad decisions to this end equation 3
supposes that the agent learns from the
failure of decisions by assuming that
the bad decisions were sampled from the
opposite of the optimal policy mapping
some more details
and then
by convention
active inference uses C to denote the
prior preference
that's how we've seen the C
variable in many models as preferences
prior preference this work uses C to
denote a mapping to determine a decision
depending on the previous state
herein the prior preference is implicit
in the risk function
due to construction
see
does not explicitly appear in the
inference thus it is omitted in the
following formulations
so that's a key point about the notation
of the variable C and something kind of
maybe interesting to explore
equation four
variational Bayesian inference refers to
the process that optimizes the posterior
belief Q of data based on based on the
mean field approximation Q of theta is
expressed as and here is the
factorization
representation
of the Q of theta variational
and another notation note throughout the
manuscript bold case variables such as
bold S Sub Tau denote the posterior
expectations of the corresponding italic
case random variables
and some more details about the model
for example for Simplicity here we
suppose that state indecision priors D
and E are fixed so one could imagine
they don't have to be but for Simplicity
they will be here
under the above defined generative model
and posterior beliefs the ensuring
variational free energy is analytically
expressed as follows equation five
this is a variational free energy f
and recall equation one that it is being
connected to
juxtaposed with Etc
the loss function
the gradient descent on variational free
energy
updates the posterior beliefs about
hidden States s decisions Delta and
parameters Theta
the optimal posterior beliefs that
minimize variational free energy are
obtained as the fixed point of the
implicit gradient descent which ensures
that change in F with respect to the
change in Hidden State through time
equals zero
and some more definitions all of them
are zero that one might be an O but
they're all zero
and this is saying the ball rolls to the
bottom of the hill
in this gradient descents and when the
rate of change is zero then that is a
fixed point a tractor-like dynamic and
that can be used
as a way to incrementally fit
statistical models
like the loss function is used to
incrementally fit
neural networks
to explicitly demonstrate the formal
correspondence with the cost function
for neural networks considered in the
next section we further transformed the
variational free energy as follows
some details
using these relationships equation 5 is
transformed into the form shown in
figure three
see the methods section variational free
energy for further details
in what follows we demonstrate that the
internal states of canonical neural
networks and code posterior beliefs
here's figure three
on the top from the caption figure three
is the mathematical mathematical
equivalence between variational free
energy and neural network cost functions
depicted by one-to-one correspondence of
their components top
variational free energy transformed from
equation 5 using the Bayes theorem
and
foreshadowing equation seven using this
relationship equation seven is
transformed into the form presented at
the bottom of the figure
so here's F variational free energy and
L the neural network cost function and
different elements as they're
represented here
with some
resonances and concordance and Beyond
which we can explore
there being
shown to be equivalent
and it was in the conversation preparing
for this
dot zero with Dean where
we saw this as some chromosomes
in the section canonical neural networks
perform active inference in this section
we identify the neuronal substrates that
correspond to components of the active
inference scheme to find above we
consider a class of two-layer neural
networks with our current Connections in
the middle layer figure 1A those are
those
connections with loops recurrent in the
middle layer
the modeling of the networks in this
section referred to as canonical neural
networks is based on the following three
assumptions that reflect physiological
knowledge
one gradient descent on a cost function
L determines the updates of neural
activity and synoptic weights method
section neural networks
neural 2 assumption 2 neural activity is
updated by the weighted sum of inputs
and its fixed point is expressed in a
form of the sigmoid or logistic function
and assumption 3 a modulatory factor
mediates synaptic plasticity in a
post-hoc manner
they write based upon assumption 2 which
is neural activity is updated by the
weighted sum of inputs and its fixed
point
is expressed in the form of a sigmoid or
logistic function
based on assumption 2 we formulate
neural activity in the middle layer and
output layer
the autonomous States as follows
equation six
without loss of generality
equation 6 can be cast as the gradient
descent on cost function l
such a cost function can be identified
by simply integrating the right hand
side of equation 6 with respect to X and
Y consistent with previous treatments
citations
because neural activity and synaptic
plasticity minimize the same cost
function l
the derivatives of L must generate the
modulated synaptic plasticity
under these constraints reflecting
assumptions one through three a class of
cost functions is identified as follows
equation seven loss function
awesome to hear somebody read this
directly
so there's a firing rate aspect
that's related to neural firing
in the short term
more perceptual aspect of function and
there's a slower
neurotransmitter neuroglial Factor
mediated
learning
over perhaps a different time scale and
with some different features and they're
being included as a joint model of
inference and here that is being
connected to doing inference on action
synaptic plasticity in neural networks
so synaptic plasticity rules conjugate
to the above rate coding model can now
be expressed as a gradient descent on
the same cost function L according to
assumption one
equations eight and nine
showing that
neural networks can integrate those
modes of firing rate like and
synoptomodulatory like
neural networks cost functions and
variational free energy
based on the above considerations we now
establish the formal correspondence
between the neural network cost function
and variational free energy
using under the aforementioned three
minimal assumptions we identified the
neural network cost function as equation
7. equation 7 can be transformed into
the form shown in figure 3 bottomed
using sigmoid functions of synaptic
strengths
so equation 7 loss function
transformed into the form shown in
figure three
bottom
uh
hence
this class of cost functions for
canonical neural networks is formally
homologous to variational free energy
under the particular form of the pomdp
generative model defined in the previous
section
we obtained this result based on
analytic derivations without reference
to the complete class theorem thereby
confirming the proposition of equation
one
loss function and free energy
this in turn suggests that any canonical
neural network in this class is
implicitly performing active inference
table 2 summarizes the correspondence
between the quantities of the neural
network and their homologs in
variational base
so two
a great concordance table
on the left side neural network
formation
on the right side variational Bayes
formulation
so
just like in figure three we had
the
two long lines
then
table two
we have
rotated 90 degrees
and the variables for different
parts of these models
are
laid next to each other
so
what papers
of neural networks
can we make
active models for
is it already done
or is there just one
script that needs to be done
and then conversely what interesting
variational Bayesian models
have
interesting applications or
some other value or Information Gain
from being cast as neural networks or
integrating neural networks into
what had previously been
only analytical variational Bayesian
models as well as the empirical data
fitting aspect which is related that's
highlighted by the authors
so in summary when a neural network
minimizes the cost function with respect
to its activity and plasticity
the network self-organizes to furnish
responses that minimize the risk
implicit in the cost function this
biological optimization is identical to
variational free energy minimization
under a particular form
of the pomdp model
hence this equivalence indicates that
minimizing the expected risk through
variational free energy minimization is
an inherent property of canonical neural
networks featuring delayed modulation of
hemian plasticity
okay
brief second to view some image memes
and take a breath in a stretch
on the left side the top panel says
every neural network is implicitly
performing active inference question
mark that's awesome
in the middle image meme one simply
makes a neural network
and it is implicitly performing active
inference
also question mark
and then in the right image meme there
are two pieces of paper neural network
and implicit performance of active
inference corporate needs you to find
the differences between this picture and
this picture
and here is the paper
there the same picture
so the previous sections have
successfully extended
The variational Bays meets inference
neural network
result from the 2020 paper
with an action
Loop
and a loss function only on the
autonomous States
so that was the conceptual and Technical
feature that this paper
brought in
again it'll be awesome to hear the
author describe it more and differently
and then in this part of this of the
paper they turn from that kind of
analytical theoretical
towards some numerical simulations
in Matlab
here we demonstrate the performance of
canonical neural networks using maze
tasks as an example of a delayed reward
task
the agent comprised the aforementioned
canonical neural networks
figure 4A thus it implicitly performs
active inference by minimizing
variational free energy so now some
entity or agent is going to be
constructed and numerically simulated
to support
some of the uh
aspects of their model and point towards
utility
in other settings so here's figure four
simulation of neural network solving
maze tasks
uh in part A there's the architecture of
the agent
sensory input layer o of t
synaptic weights
into the middle layer X internal States
and the output layer y decision action
with risk
gamma of t
the sensation comes in a neural network
then outputs a decision
there's some uh task that the entity
must
perform
which is
uh
to move towards the goal from the start
across this lateral maze
so one can imagine that
if it were just a hallway with no
maze features
simple strategies would be very overfit
but effective like always move simply
towards the goal
whereas in more complex settings which
this is an example of
where there's uncertainty as well as
many local Optima
so one has to sometimes take one or two
or three or four or more steps or
however many
to get closer to the goal
and sometimes may not know for example
how long those
backtracking
situations are going to be
and all these other complexities for
which this maze example
is
similar symbolum uh symbolic of so maybe
there's some some interesting Mythos
maze connections and computational
and here's some
performance
measures on the maze task
with the neural network entity this way
before training the agent moved to a
random Direction each step resulting in
a failure to reach the goal position
right and within the time limit during
training the neural network updated
synaptic strengths depending on its
neural activity and ensuring outcomes
I.E risk
this this training comprised a cycle of
action and learning phases
this treatment renders neural activity
and adaptive behaviors of the agent
highly explainable and manipulatable in
terms of the appropriate prior beliefs
implicit in firing thresholds for a
given task or environment in other words
these results suggest that firing
thresholds are the neuronal substrates
that encode State and decision priors as
predicted mathematically
big if true
furthermore
when the updating of parameters is slow
across these two now linked domains
parameters of the variational Bayesian
autonomous State inference and the
neural network loss function parameters
when the updating of these parameters
are slow in relation to the experimental
observations
the parameters can be estimated through
Bayesian inference based on empirically
observed neuronal responses see method
section data analysis for details
using this approach we estimated
implicit prior e which is encoded by PSI
from sequences of neural activity
generated from the synthetic neural
networks used in the simulations
reported in figure 4. we confirmed that
this estimator was a good approximation
to the true e
so that's also pretty interesting this
is showing
they don't just lay out this
architecture
and show that it's possible to fulfill
this maze task with the best
whatever
it's not a classification accuracy
imperative alone
they're describing that from
empirically observed neuronal responses
which is to say the experimenter's
observation
the sequences of neural activity
generated from the synthetic neural
networks used in that figure
numerically
so statistically that estimator was a
good approximation to the true e figure
five a
so here's figure five
uh estimation of implicit priors enables
the prediction of subsequent learning
so that's pretty interesting
and will be great to hear what each of
the axes are
and what all the variables mean
with this setup in place they did some
numerical validation
and talked a little bit more about
fitting
data
from this simulation model
here's the discussion section
so the first paragraph of the discussion
biological organisms formulate plans to
minimize future risks in this work we
captured this characteristic in
biologically plausible terms under
minimal assumptions
we derive simple differential equations
that can be plausibly interpreted in
terms of a neural network architecture
that entails degrees of freedom with
respect to certain free parameters EG
firing threshold
these free parameters play the role of
Prior beliefs in variational Bayesian
formulation
thus the accuracies of inferences and
decisions depend upon prior beliefs
implicit in neural networks
and here's some more stable diffusion
and neural network
aunt's brain neural network
so some more summarization of what they
did
based on the view of the brain as an
agent that performs Bayesian inference
neuronal implementations of Bayesian
belief updating have been proposed
which enables neural networks to store
and recall spiking sequences eight learn
temporal Dynamics and causal hierarchy
nine extract hidden causes 10 solve maze
tasks 11 and make plans to control
robots 12. so citations 8 through 12
listed here
in these approaches the update rules are
generally derived from Bayesian cost
functions EG variational free energy
however the precise relationship between
these update rules and the neural
activity and plasticity of canonical
neural networks has yet to be fully
established
we identified a one-to-one
correspondence between neural network
architecture and a specific pomdp
implicit in that Network
equation 2 speaks to a unique pomdp
model consistent with the neural network
architecture defined in equation 6.
where their correspondences are
summarized in table 2. and the figures
this means that our scheme can be used
to identify the form of the pomdp
given an observable circuit structure
moreover the free parameters that
parameterize equation 6 can be estimated
using equation 24.
this means that the generative model and
ensuring variational free energy can in
principle be reconstructed from
empirical data
this offers a formal characterization of
implicit Bayesian models entailed by
neural circuits thereby enabling a
prediction of subsequent learning so
what can be done with this
what is this
new new
what is new here
does this second selection
fully establish the precise relationship
between these update rules
and the neural activity and plasticity
of canonical neural networks
here is a discussion section on hebian
plasticity neurotransmitters and glia
with a lot of citations listed
and here is just one interesting
follow-on discussion from the
computational aspects neuro cognitive
and computational aspects of heavy and
plasticity
is these modulations have been observed
empirically with various neural
modulators and neurotransmitters such as
dopamine
noradrenaline muscarine and Gaba as well
as glial factors
so here's a picture by Alexandra
michaelva cultured astrostites
release signaling and growth factors
that regulate proper neuronal
development so cool
glial pick
dopamine and reinforcement learning in
particular a delayed modulation of
synoptic plasticity is well known with
dopamine neurons citations 35 through
37.
those citations are listed here
this speaks to a learning scheme that is
conceptually distinct from standard
reinforcement learning algorithms such
as the temporal difference learning with
actor critic models based on state
action value functions
pre please see the previous work
citation 50. for a detailed comparison
between active inference and
reinforcement learning
that is Sajid Bal par and friston active
inference demystified and compared from
2021 and that's also active model stream
number 2.1
we mathematically demonstrated that such
plasticity enhances the association
between the pre-post mapping and the
future value of the modulatory factor
where the latter is cast as a risk
function
this means that postsynaptic neurons
self-organized to react in a manner that
minimizes future risk
so the neural network had three layers
it's the second and the third layer not
the initial sensory layer but the second
and the third layer
the cognitive and the active States
which are the autonomous States of
the particular States
so that's
um
quite interesting
the self-organization of postsynaptic
neurons
to react in a manner that minimizes
future risk
crucially this computation corresponds
formally to variational Bayesian
inference under a particular form of
pomdp generative models suggesting that
the delayed modulation of habibian
plasticity
is a realization of active inference
and
regionally specific projections of
neuromodulators may allow each brain
region to optimize activity to minimize
risk and leverage a hierarchical
generative model implicit in cortical
and subcortical hierarchies
this is reminiscent of theories of
neuromodulation and meta learning
developed previously citation 52 doya
2002.
meta learning and neuromodulation
cool
our work may be potentially useful when
casting these theories in terms of
generative models and variational free
energy minimization
they then return the discussion to the
complete class theorem in neural
networks so the complete class theorem
same citations from before
ensures that any neural network whose
activity and plasticity minimize the
same cost function can be cast as
performing Bayesian inference
however identifying the implicit
generative model that underwrites any
canonical neural network is a more
delicate problem because the theorem
does not specify a form of the
generative model for a given canonical
neural network
which is pretty interesting
is that to say that the form of the
generative model as modeled
is different in what ways from
the given canonical neural network
the posterior beliefs are largely shaped
by prior beliefs making it challenging
to identify the generative model by
simply observing systemic Dynamics to
this end it is necessary to commit to a
particular form of the generative model
and elucidate how posterior beliefs are
encoded or parameterized by the neural
network States
this work addresses these issues by
establishing a reverse engineering
approach to identify a generative model
implicit in a canonical neural network
thereby establishing one-to-one
correspondences between their components
remarkably a network of rate coding
models with sigmoid activation function
formally corresponds to a class of pomdp
models
which provide an analytically tractable
example of the present equivalence
please refer to the previous paper
citation 22 for further discussion
so some of the analytical details
especially on the inferential
side
cognitive
Burr captured in the earlier paper
this paper goes further into
mapping the
potentially necessary and sufficient
aspects of
particular entity
which is to say the risk minimizing
features of the autonomous states with
respect to the entire particular States
including sensory States
connecting that
back of the envelope
verbally expressible formulation
to
some complete class of neural networks
so what's outside of the complete class
and why and then what groups within the
class have special or different
features
it is remarkable that the proposed
equivalence can be leveraged to identify
a generative model that an arbitrary
neural network implicitly employs this
contrasts with naive neural network
models that address only the Dynamics of
neural activity and plasticity
if the generative model differs from the
true generative process
that generates the sensory input
inferences and decisions are biased I.E
sub-optimal relative to Bayes optimal
inferences and decisions based upon the
right sort of beliefs prior beliefs
in general the implicit priors may or
may not be equal to the true priors thus
a generic neural network is typically
sub-optimal
nevertheless these implicit priors can
be optimized by updating free parameters
EG threshold factors
Phi PSI
based on the gradient descent on cost
function l by updating the free
parameters the network will eventually
in principle
become Bayes optimal for any given task
in essence when the cost function is
minimized with respect to neural
activity
synaptic strengths and any other
constants that characterize the cost
function
the cost function becomes equivalent to
variational free energy with the optimal
prior beliefs
so the cost function
for the neural network activity and
synaptic strengths
underlying
the loss function
R equivalent to
the kind of gradient descent
enabled variational free energy
minimization
under the Bayes optimality
scenario
from a risk perspective
simultaneously the expected risk is
minimized because variational free
energy is minimized only when the when
the Precision of the risk gamma
is maximized
see method section generative model for
further details
very interesting
they then say
the class of neural networks we consider
can be viewed as a class of reservoir
Networks
citation 54 citation 55. here
the proposed equivalence could render
such Reservoir Networks explainable
and may provide the optimal plasticity
rules for these networks to minimize
future risk
by using the formal analogy to
variational free energy minimization
under the particular form of pomdp
models
a clear interpretation of reservoir
networks remains an important open issue
in computational neuroscience
in machine learning
so from Wikipedia Reservoir Computing is
a framework for computation derived from
recurrent neural network theory that
Maps input signals into higher
dimensional computational spaces through
the Dynamics of a fixed non-linear
system called a reservoir
after the input signal is fed into the
reservoir which is treated as a block
box a simple readout mechanism is
trained to read the state of the
reservoir and map it to the desired
output
then there's two key benefits of this
approach
the first key benefit of this framework
is that training is performed only at
the readout stage as the reservoir
Dynamics are fixed
the second is that the computational
power of naturally available systems
both classical and quantum mechanical
can be used to reduce the effective
computational cost
here's some stable diffusion
Reservoir Computing active inference
neural network
so this would be interesting to discuss
and I remember some octave Institute
participants who are specifically
interested
empirical analyzes and hypotheses
they write the equivalence between
neural network Dynamics and gradient
flows on variational free energy is
empirically testable using
electrophysiological recordings or
functional Imaging of brain activity
so
then another
summarization crucially
the proposed equivalence guarantees that
an arbitrary neural network that
minimizes its cost function
possibly implemented in biological
organisms or neuromorphic Hardware can
be cast as performing variational
Bayesian inference so
to State it a few more times in the
final paragraph
in summary a class of biologically
plausible cost functions for canonical
neural networks can be cast as
variational free energy
formal correspondences exist between
priors posteriors and cost functions
this means that canonical neural
networks that optimize their cost
functions implicitly perform active
inference
this approach enables identification of
the implicit generative model and
reconstruction of variational free
energy that neural networks employ
this means that in principle neural
activity behavior and learning through
plasticity can be predicted under Bayes
optimality assumptions
there's a Code availability statement
the Matlab scripts are available at
GitHub
in the
repo of the first author and it would be
awesome
or the author or anyone to
bring this
working Matlab script up
and see if we could do some
real time
active inference
then as mentioned earlier
from the roadmap the methods are
following the discussion
I'll just show the equations but not go
into any details because there's not
time nor
familiarity so those who have more of
one or the other would be welcome to
fill in some dots
because this is a really awesome and
important paper so I hope that it can be
interpreted and critiqued and elaborated
on
and so on
by those with familiarity in both sides
of that free energy loss function
equation one
generative model section many details
are provided equation 10 is shown it's a
larger unpacking of the generative model
section variational free energy many
details are provided equation 11 12 13
14 and 15.
section inference and learning details
are provided equations 16 17 18.
then section on neural networks so
there's just some interesting writing
here so I wanted to highlight that
in this section we elaborate the
one-to-one correspondences between
components of the canonical neural
networks and variational Bays via an
analytically tractable model so that's
the figure three
that we've been returning to
neurons respond quickly to a continuous
stimulus stream with the time scale
faster than typical changes in sensory
input
for instance a peak of spiking neurons
in the visual cortex of V1 appears
within 50 and 80 milliseconds after a
visual stimulation
citation 6263
which is substantially faster than the
temporal autocorrelation time scale of
natural image sequences about 500
milliseconds citation 6465
so that's pretty interesting
what is the temporal autocorrelation
time scale of natural sequences
what time scale do neural firing
and neuroplasticity
Etc processes actually occur at
and when my
some type of function at a given time
scale
be understood to be functional or not
thus in other words Downstream
of the fact that neurons respond quickly
at a time scale faster than typical
changes in sensory input
we consider the case where the neural
activity converges to a fixed Point
given a sensory stimulus
we note that the present equivalence is
derived from the differential equations
equation six but not from its fixed
point
thus the equivalence holds true
irrespective of the time constant of
neurons
to rephrase neural networks with a large
time constant
normally correspond to Bayesian belief
updating with a large time constant
which implies an ins insufficient
coverage of the posterior beliefs
pretty interesting
related to learning rates
and Bayesian updating rates
and all of the
nooks and crannies of Bayesian inference
and the challenges associated with
Dynamic uncertain rugged
Fitness and free energy landscapes
these optimization challenges
which are addressed differently
methodologically culturally Etc in the
variational Bayesian and in the neural
cases
they
have to deal with time
and so all of those different nooks and
crannies mentions like catastrophic
learning catastrophic forgetting simply
memory anticipation attention
local Maxima
choosing when to play all these higher
order questions
are connected here
does that make it what kind of a problem
space now
or just what kind of space
pretty interesting
and equation 19 20 21 22 23.
they have some more details on the
simulation
maybe we could see the simulation go
and in the last section
data analysis so this is kind of
returning to that point about the time
constants
in Bayesian and neural network systems
when the belief updating of implicit
priors d and e is slow in relation to
experimental observations
d and e which are encoded by Phi and PSI
can be viewed as being fixed over a
short period of time as an analogy to
homeostatic plasticity over longer time
scales 66.
homeostatic plasticity in the developing
nervous system 2004.
very interesting in light of our
recent discussions on allostasis and
other topics
thus
Phi and PSI can be statistically
estimated by a conventional Bayesian
inference or maximum likelihood
estimation given a flat prior based on
empirically observed neuronal responses
in this case the estimators of Phi and
PSI are obtained as follows
nice equation number 24 mentioned
earlier
so that will be definitely one two
look into more
well
I hope you found this a useful
and interesting dot zero
I'm looking forward to the discussion
with the author and again any other
Institute participants or those with
knowledge or strong
feelings to express about neural
networks active inference applied active
inference
computational modeling of perception
cognition and action
neural networks in the wild
AI ethics all these different areas
can
hopefully have a nice discussion
in
51.1 and 0.2
that'll be the last paper streams
for 2022
there will still be a few guest streams
upcoming
so those discussions will close the
paper
focused prepared live streams for 2022
and yeah if you want to be more involved
with live streams whenever you're
listening to this
join
or recommend someone to join or help in
any number of other ways
just listening and learning is awesome
and we also really look forward to those
who want to help make some of these
connections that are latent and
sometimes exposed in these papers and
conversations
and with a few motivated people who want
to connect for example to the neural
network
communities
and those who can facilitate discussions
on these topics
that would be awesome
just
using my final thoughts on this dot zero
because it's always great to have others
also join in the preparation for the dot
zero so just wants to add that note on
this rare solo stream so thanks again
looking forward to
talking or seeing you later bye